this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers are you ready it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris choose your language
choose your tools choose your
environment collaborate build faster and
deploy more efficiently when you can
make faster decisions there's no telling
what he'll create ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems comm
slash try to try iris for software
engineering radio this is Adam Gordon
Bell Alex
Petroff is a data infrastructure
engineer he is a database and storage
system enthusiast he is a Cassandra a
core contributor and the author of
database internals a new book fro Riley
Alex welcome to the podcast
yeah hey pleasure to be here databases
have a lot of components in them like
query optimizers clustering transaction
management access levels but I thought
it'd be interesting today since you're
the expert just to talk about kind of
the storage layer writing to disk
basically that's my favorite part
so what is the database storage engine
so the database storage engine is sort
of something that lives in the heart of
the database in the very end so if you
can say that you are the user and you're
sending their request and probably
storage is the last thing that well
actually your request gets to so and so
it's like the furthest or the farthest
distance from you to there basically so
in short a storage engine is something
that helps you to access your data and
it also communicates and is coupled
somewhat tightly with many
other components of the database such as
for instance right ahead log or it can
even be considered a part of the storage
engine or it is coupled in a way with
the transactional processor so yeah it's
something that helps you to store the
data and well get it back whenever you
need it
when I when I think of storage engine as
concept I think of back when I used my
sequel and you could actually like pick
a different storage engine is that is
that common in databases that they could
have interchangeable storage engines I
wish I wish I wish that was true so
there I would say is a concept of
interchangeable a search engine in
several databases and for example
MongoDB is probably somewhat famous for
having several search engines or at
least you know they migrated from one to
another so they're using wire tiger at
the moment as to my best knowledge at
least and before that they were using em
map search engine and some well storage
engines are targeting themselves or
positioning themselves as a component
that can be simply dropped in well some
database so unfortunately I cannot say
that most databases allow you know just
dropping in and easily replacing the
storage engine that they're using but
there are some and there are obviously
use cases for that and one probably most
prominent example is Roxy V and there is
a project called Rock Sandra for example
that is taking Cassandra and trying to
make the storage engine of Cassandra
pluggable and unfortunately that's not
such an easy task and it is allegedly
used in production I don't have any
details on that but well it's an open
source project and it seems like it's
active and living but from the
perspective of like development it was
not you know just abstracting away the
difficult parts and making it completely
100% blockable so there
are many things that I would say still
not 100% compatible between you know
earlier traditional Cassandra in air
quotes and the rock Sandra I hope that
the trend continues and more folks
actually try and make their search
engines pluggable and start using you
know off-the-shelf while ready to use
solutions maybe Roxy B Anwar Tiger to be
the best contender so to say so yeah
there are examples I assume it's not as
easy as some interface with like write
and read and you just implement them and
it's over yes I would say that that's
that's the biggest problem and once
again as I said the coupling between the
database components is probably one of
the biggest problems yeah we don't get
to arbitrarily pick and choose because
they don't we can't switch them out what
about the storage engine of like an
in-memory database how does that differ
so when we're talking about in memory
databases it's not like you can say that
every in-memory database is the same so
some in-memory databases store data just
in memory so there is no access to disk
at all and some in-memory databases use
this for some of the things so for
example you can use disk for logging
like recovery right so whenever you
restart the database you can bring it at
least to the latest state that it's been
in before it was restarted or another
example is whenever you're using disk as
a secondary storage meaning that most of
the data is living in memory and the
rest of the data so sorts a cold storage
lives on disk so when we're talking
about like in-memory databases there are
just so many things and in my opinion
the storage engine part of in-memory
databases is probably still the thing
that is taking care of sort of disk
accesses because well everything above
it it can be thought of as you know
several levels of maybe exquisite cache
like very best quick and specialized
caches in a way but ultimately if you
are accessing the disk in the end I
would say that storage engine is still
something that well is below the
in-memory caches however I'm not ten
percent sure if there is you know such
strict separation of concepts or
depending on an implementation things
can be titled or tied together so
tightly that it's barely possible to
tell those things apart so yeah it
really depends so does that mean that
there could be some sort of convergence
like if I am able to give enough memory
to a Cassandra instance and use it as a
key value store does it perform like
like Redis or I would say that it's very
difficult to make Cassandra perform just
like Redis on like if we compare like a
single node of Redis and some little
node of Cassandra with a bunch of memory
but I would say that cassandra has its
own features and its own things that it
can be better at I guess I'm imagining
in my head that I could make an
in-memory key value store by just having
just like a hash map that I hold on to
right and put values in and out whereas
like a disk based storage engine seems
much more complex that I mean that's my
understanding is it is it harder to work
with a database that's storing things on
disk versus one that's in memory I would
say it's inherently harder so much much
harder so it's funny that you mentioned
the hash table because like one of the
things it's best for it's good for is
like random access basically right
whenever you have a key and you would
like to get a value so that would be the
perfect example for the hash map usage
however if you would like to take not a
single key but the range of keys for
instance you know give me everybody with
the last name that starts with P for
instance so it would be very difficult
to well respond to the same query with a
hash map or at least you would have to
have either you know a linear scan
through all the keys and values or you
would have to you know have some
separate index structure that would sort
things and prepare them in a way that
would allow such a query to be ran
however if we're talking about the on
disk like structures so things get even
you know more complicated so not only
we're or we're not only constrained by
the fact that well certain data
structures are best for certain things
but we are also constrained by the fact
that we are implementing the memory
management by ourselves because even if
we're using the programming language
with unmanaged runtime whatever we are
just using you know we're all pointers
for instance and we still get at least
something from the system right we get
like virtual memory we can access well
we can allocate chunks of memory we free
them and we don't really see you know
physical representation of things most
of the time and even if we're talking
about things like a classes and
structures so we are writing two fields
and we rarely you know address things
just you just byte by byte and whenever
we're talking about a memory or things
that are stored on disk we have to
implement our own memory management
meaning that whenever we address things
that are located within the same page on
the disk we can you know use like local
pointers whenever we address the thing
that is located in a different page on a
disk we have to use out of page pointers
that and we have to think about how we
implement those because you know page
location can change so of course I'm you
know just throwing concepts here but the
idea right so instead of simply
allocating and deallocating chunks of
memory you have to you know think
through an entire structure basically
how to lay it out on the disk and very
little is there to help you because file
system all it gives you is an interface
of you know seek to a specific point in
the file and read a certain number of
bytes from that
and then well you can write basically to
the same location in the file and that's
all you get from it right and everything
that you implement in the file like its
header
it's like trailer and everything in
between those is pretty much like your
pages and it's it is certainly much more
difficult than implementing and in
memory data structure however a memory
data structures implement it right and
especially when like there is lots of
concurrency involved I would say that
it's also not such an easy task it's
just different sets of problems so to
say so in a programming languages have a
lot of concepts for dealing with memory
right like even just we have pointers
that we can follow it but on disk you're
saying like we have to build all these
constructs ourselves we have to build
our own little pointer you know what
this means jump to here why do we need
databases and why not just files in my
opinion main reasons for preferring a
database over flat files is like first
one is storage efficiency hmm so files
are organized in the database files are
organized in the way that minimizes this
storage overhead for a stored data
record which is not necessarily the same
for the file system the second one is
like access efficiency so records can be
located in the like smallest possible
number of steps and here I mean that can
also differ for your use case you know
depending on what exactly you would like
to achieve and the third one is update
efficiency so records updates are
performed in a way that minimizes the
number of changes on disk so you would
like to avoid you know putting extra
strain on your hardware without any need
to do that so in my opinion that sort of
summarizes so storage access and update
efficiency is sort of three reasons for
us to use files or databases as an
abstraction instead of trying to
implement or our mini database every
time we're doing it however from what I
heard many databases at least you know
in the early days of computing
so to say were implemented exactly
because somebody was tired of doing same
thing in every project they were
starting so they just decided okay I
just sit and implement a general purpose
tool a database that is going to help me
to you know
retrieve the value by a specific key
because this is what I do very often and
it turned out to be a concept that is
extremely useful for many of us today so
at some point somebody's like I'm gonna
write these records to this file and I'm
gonna need to read them in and they
start the third time they do this
they're like okay I know what I need to
do here can I abstract this and that's
your database storage engine yes and so
I assume like if I were doing that yeah
first there's some sort of mapping so
maybe if I have like some enum maybe I
want to just squish it into bits to keep
it small so I'd come up with some sort
of structure so you mentioned earlier
LSM trees versus B trees so what's a
b-tree well let me then step off you for
a sec and and let's just take one more
step back and look at what are the trees
in general and why we need them right
yeah so when we were talking for
instance about hash tables we decided or
we concluded that you know in order to
search not a single value by a single
key but like a range of values by a
specific key we need a structure that is
different from a hash map and one of the
data structures that we can implement in
memory is a tree a simplest way to
implement a tree is a binary tree right
so a node that has two children
basically is a binary tree right but
whenever we're trying to is it sorted so
not necessarily so binary tree only says
that okay we have a node and two
children and they're not sorted in any
way if we would like to make it sorted
we inevitably once again sorry I keep
repeating this word gonna come to the
concept of binary search tree so why we
come to that is because binary tree is
unbalanced right so you can have more
elements on one side or on the other
and there is nothing that tries to you
know maintain some sort of order in this
structure so in order to maintain that
order we need some sort of balance tree
one of the examples of that is binary
search tree so binary search tree is a
tree which has at the root if you look
down from the root basically it's going
to have elements less than the root node
on one side and elements that are
greater than the root on the other side
so that makes it searchable right that
means that if we progress from the root
node all the way to the left you know go
following left pointers all the way to
the very bottom of the tree we're going
to reach the minimum of the tree so the
smallest key that is toward industry and
if we're doing the same for the right
like following right pointers from the
root we're going to reach the maximum of
the tree and this sort of brings us to
like the first usable searchable data
structure that is well can be used in
memory and well you can implement and
use however if you're trying to
implement binary search tree on disk
you're gonna run inevitably in several
problems because one of the things that
you're going to be facing is the fact
that because you have just you know two
pointers you are going to be constantly
moving those nodes and constantly
reassigning those pointers so whatever
for instance you have a root node and
two children and you have you know split
the child so you would have to you know
reassign all the pointers that were
related to everybody that was somehow
connected to one another and like all
these balancing operations are going to
be in a way expensive or going to be
costing because you have to write if to
rewrite it to disk exactly so that's one
one problem and the second problem is of
course locality we are not necessarily
going to have keys that are going to be
searched together written together on
the in the same page or in the same even
region on the disk or somewhere close so
we may end up actually seeking the disk
quite a lot you know just running around
and
trying to locate the things that we
would like to find because like you said
before on disk like every pointer you
just have to go to a different location
on the disk for every pointer follow in
theory yeah in theory yes of course you
can optimize for that and this is how we
sort of progress to be trees or B plus
trees so which is discussed we progress
from you know hash maps to binary trees
then to binary search trees and then we
concluded that binary search trees are
not a good fit for the disc because they
have very low fan out and potentially
bad locality and we can solve it by
basically increasing the fan out and
improving the locality right so that
that sort of means that unlike binary
search trees B trees have not just two
children but have many in binary search
tree we have a single key per node and
this key pretty much tells you like who
is in the middle of this place that
we're standing at so if we look to the
right we see you know all the values
that are smaller than and if we look at
the opposite direction we see all the
values that are larger than and so we
are always sort of standing in the
middle so hmm it's always sort of a
separator key right that splits the
range that we're searching in two parts
and unlike binary search trees B trees
have many keys and so the relationship
between the number of child nodes and
the number of keys is maintained so it's
the same as in vibrant research keys so
it means that in the binary search tree
we have a single key and two pointers
and in a b-tree we have n keys and n
plus one pointers to the children so
this sort of makes a data structure that
well first of all whenever we're
searching something we know that we can
very quickly locate the keys on this
level right because all the notes that
are required in order for us to well
reduce the search space
pretty much are located on this page so
we fetch or a read one a single page
from the disk and then load it up in
memory and then start searching this
memory segments usually we use something
like a binary search because all the
keys are sorted and then we locate the
searched key and this key has a pointer
a child pointer that is attached to this
key and then we follow the child pointer
to the next level and then on the next
level we do the same thing we load an
entire page we binary search Keys find
the key that well is pretty much
matching whatever we're searching once
again follow the pointer that is
attached to this key all the way to well
the bottom of the tree to the leaf node
where we can finally find the data so
and once again we have more than one key
per node and we have many children and
this sort of solves all the problems
that we had with the binary search trees
because we can seek from disk kind of
this big chunk that is our our children
pointers and go through them all yes in
one pass I think that so now you know if
I'm a database engine so I'm using my B
tree I have less changes when a key
comes in like if I want to insert
something new there's less changes but
it still has to happen I assume we have
a maximum size than any node will have
in terms of children and if I get a new
element that would be sorted into the
middle of a full page then then what do
I do
so you know whenever we were talking
about the binary search trees we briefly
mentioned I think I even slipped and
said that splits and merges however
there are obviously no splits and virtus
in the binary search trees so what
binary search trees do in order to you
know increase the capacity they sort of
append the nodes to all the bottom most
level or wherever it fits basically and
then they rotate so rotation step is a
way to balance the tree and so this is
how pretty much the tree is growing
right so on each step you can append the
note and make the tree sort of
unbalanced by making one leg of the tree
slightly longer than the other ones so
yeah basically what we do is we take the
midpoint and leave it in this page that
we were splitting then we take like all
the elements before the midpoint and put
it to like the first page that we append
basically as a child to these page that
we just split which has only one element
now and then we take the rest of the
elements that were in that page and
append it to the yet another page and
now we have sort of instead of having
just one page we have three pages and of
course in order to outgrow the capacity
of this tree we we will have to perform
you know more operations because now we
increase the capacity of the tree
significantly and that's one of the
advantages of the B+ tree is that
basically the capacity of the tree grows
exponentially as the number of levels is
increasing which is the advantage like
if I understand because that's like in a
traditional spinning hard disk that's
gonna be like fewer seeks right cuz you
only have to go down say three levels or
something exactly exactly so what what
you usually end up doing is you end up
you know reading maybe four five pages
depending on the depth of your tree but
basically you're going to in terms of
disk seeks you're going to have as many
disk seeks as you have levels I mean
there are of course edge cases as
everywhere everywhere to whatever I'm
saying but in a general case that's
that's true yeah so now I understand
like I made my storage engine I have
some sort of file I sweat my file up
into pages I'm gonna use those pages to
make this tree so that I can update
right things and certain things we
haven't tucked up we haven't talked
about indexes so how would I represent
an index okay well first of all the
question is gonna be haven't we really
talked about indexes are you sure about
that so maybe we were talking about
indexes all the time in
and thing is that there is a very fine
line between indexes and tables in fact
it's very difficult to actually find the
difference and some of the indexes are
actually just tables is just like tables
inverted by a specific key so if you are
thinking about like a table with some
sort of a primary key it's nothing but a
bunch of you know data that is indexed
by a primary key so in the end this is
sort of an index so usually we're
talking about index organized tables
which people usually say just tables and
whenever we're talking about indexes
we're usually talking about something a
structure that points to the index
organized table and even here we have we
can have potentially like several
distinctions one of the ways to
implement this is going to be an index
that is holding a primary key hmm which
uniquely identifies the record and the
other one is storing a pointer on disk
basically where the record can be found
and the difference between these two
approaches is as follows in first case
whenever we're storing the key of the
record that can be located we have to
perform sort of extra steps right for
instance during the read yeah what we
have to like read like whenever we probe
the index and we found that okay the
primary key of the record that we would
like to find is such-and-such
then we go to index organized table and
find this record right hmm but whenever
we update we have to go back to the
index and update okay and say that these
keys or these values are are not indexed
this way anymore so we sort of have to
keep the index in sync with the index
organized table because they moved right
for instance we were indexing people by
their zip code right and somebody has
moved and that means that a specific
person that was previously found by a
specific ID
has moved from one zip to the other one
that means that an index with like zip
codes or index by zip code has to be
updated and the record with this person
has to be removed from the history or
their previous zip code and added to
their new zip code so that's one of the
things and if we once again take a
different approach that I just briefly
mentioned and we are storing the pointer
directly to basically where the data
record is stored obviously we will still
have to update the index in order to all
say for instance if the person has moved
so we would have to move it from one
index bucket to the other one so this
has no implications in this case if we
are storing the direct disk offset we
can just bypass searching the index
organized table that means that we can
after we found the position of the
record on disk we can just you know go
ahead and read it so we don't have to
Serge this index organized table anymore
so in short coming back once again add
to the your question about indexes and
whether or not we talked about them so
indexes are sort of same you know so you
can actually have B 3 B plus 3 indexes
let me make sure that I understand the B
tree example of indexes so I have I have
my user table and I'm gonna store that
as like the B+ tree on disk say I have a
auto-increment ID or something right so
my my tree is sorted using the ID and
that's my primary key so I understand
that so it's easy to look up by primary
key I want to add an index on zip code
so you're saying in fact it's all the
same thing you just make another B tree
but now the key is zip code so we have
it sorted by zip code and then I think
you're saying the distinction is where
that pointer goes to so the pointer
could either tell me the ID which then I
have to go look up again in the other B
tree yes or it could tell me like the
exact location on disk and then each one
has advantages and disadvantages I guess
right exactly yes
so you just describe to use cases I can
actually
we add the third one so what we gonna do
this time is let's just expand a little
bit on your use case so we have you know
first and name last name zip code and
you know some Auto increment ID what we
can do is create an index by zip code
and then instead of storing either
pointers or IDs we're gonna store an
entire like rest of the record
so we basically say I don't know your
zip code and then pretty much your name
your first name your last name and maybe
even your ID for you know some extra
information or just for maintenance
purposes so you can do virtually
anything because it's just a matter of
how you're going to be accessing things
so the advantage of the very first
approach meaning that whenever we build
a index by zip code and are storing just
an ID of the record in the main table
the biggest advantage of that is of
course that we don't have to duplicate
the data right we have the record
recorded just once
yeah the disadvantage of this specific
approach is that we have to look up the
table right so the main table whenever
after searching the index so we sort of
do two to e traversals potentially in
order to mitigate this second tree
traversal what we can do is we can store
the pointer to this structure from index
directly the offset to the disk where
the record is stored but obviously in
this case we're coupling these two
tables very tightly then that means that
whenever one is updated the second one
just cannot be out of sync or we should
come up with some sort of a mechanism
that would you know a gracefully
fallback in case this page was relocated
or record was removed or something
different has happened so and the third
approach is whenever we are duplicating
the data and in favor of you know either
doing a second lookup or doing anything
else
so we are duplicating the data and we
don't have to
do ii seek so yeah these three
approaches are in my opinion commonly
used and some of the databases even
allow you to explicitly you know
configure these things so you basically
can say what sort of index you can
you're creating and in which way and as
far as I remember like what database
lets you choose as far as remember even
my scale let me dig it out for you and
if we can add it to the show notes later
on I will definitely do that and what I
wanted to mention here is there was a
blog post I think from uber where they
were discussing exactly the difference
exactly that difference between you know
different databases I think was my
school and Postgres and an implication
of you know either storing a direct
pointer or you know referencing things
through a level of indirection so it was
not exactly the same thing but it was in
sort of similar realme I think that it
was related to addressing the values
through the interaction table or in the
primary key calling all developers
there's no telling what you can create
when you upgrade your data platform to
inner systems iris are you ready to
build the applications you want however
you want them are you ready to develop
applications faster than ever
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner systems iris data platform ready
set code start coding for free visit
inner systems.com slash try to try iris
there seems to be a tension here which I
saw in your books well like a read
versus write efficiency tension so where
if you duplicate things into your index
right it makes writing data or updating
data more expensive but reading faster
so yeah there is always a tension
between reading and updating and in fact
there is a conjecture which is called to
rum conjecture it states that we have
three like a triangle of things
that are interconnected read
amplification write amplification and
memory amplification or read update
amplification and memory amplification
and the these three things are connected
in a way that if you have an improvement
in two of these you will inevitably
negatively influence the third one so
it's just saying that you cannot really
have all three at the same time so you
cannot be like as efficient as you would
like to be in terms of both reads and
updates and memory at the same time so
you have to make a compromise you have
to choose and the this paper about this
ROM conjecture is very interesting and
it brings up you know several topics
that probably are of use for anybody who
is who has something to do with either
databases or backends in general and I
definitely recommend to read it if you
haven't yet and one of the probably most
widely known or discussed examples is of
course the dichotomy of LSM versus
b-trees meaning that B trees are
allegedly heavily read optimized and the
LSM trees are heavily write optimized
that sounds like a good transition I
think so
what is an LSM tree okay so yeah now we
have to talk about like yet another sort
of the tree if you take B tree and then
you would like to say let's make the
pages of this B 3 immutable meaning that
whatever you make it change to the the
page you are not going to you know find
the same location in the file and try to
overwrite it instead like every page is
just you know going to be a completely
new instance of the page appended to the
end of the file right if we just do that
we end up doing so called copy-on-write
b trees right because whenever we want
to modify the page we're just creating a
sort of parallel universe of pages that
are on the way from the root to the leaf
of the note that we just updated and
then we create this parallel reality and
then we swap the pointer to the newly
created root and we have this new
beautiful copy and write immutable B+
tree so we copy all the values like
instead of changing yes a page we change
one Val we copy the whole thing change
one value exact pointer yeah so this may
sound as something like very wasteful
but because this allows you to avoid
doing something like right ahead logging
this may actually make sense for some
use cases and there are implementations
of a copy of write B trees and one of
the most permanent ones in my opinion is
LM dB
the search engine that is used in open
LDAP and there are many talks that I've
seen online on the subject and there are
some presentations that you can take out
and it's also a very interesting thing
so yeah copy-on-write v3 is a thing and
it's very useful and it's very
interesting and it's sort of a step from
mutable b tree just like with
immutability like all pages are
immutable and if we go one step further
and on top of just immutability we also
add buffering because you have noticed
that like we didn't have any buffers in
the immutable B trees because like we
don't need to buffer any data in memory
therefore we don't need the right ahead
log and we can you know just create a
parallel universe of pages and write
them in new locations and disk and this
is pretty much our log I just want to
make sure I understand this if we're
just doing some of the writes into
memory because we want to buffer it we
want to write it to disk in one shot so
we're just gonna hold it in memory then
you're saying we should also write it in
a log so that if we if we go down then
we can recover the idea exactly so but
whenever we have this buffers and
because they are memory resident and
disk based or
I mean they will eventually beat this
space as well just with the delay for
that delay we have to store this data
durably somewhere right and this is
going to be in the right a headlock so
this is one of the probably most
important parts of the storage engine or
most of the storage engines that I had
to do with so you were saying we were
doing a copy-on-write b-tree exactly yes
so we were trying to progress towards
our cemeteries and so yeah we which has
got copy-on-write be trees and we added
immutability to regular be trees and now
we're going to add also buffering on top
of that we are ending up with a thing
that is called two-component LSM trees
this is like a first thing that is
mentioned in the O'Neill's LSM tree
paper which if you haven't read just yet
I definitely advise you to read it
describes a database storage system or a
search engine you can say that splits
data in a following way some of the data
resides on the owner disk and some of
the data lives in memory and whenever a
part of like we say that the memory
table is full I don't know for instance
like larger than five megabytes it's an
arbitrary number of course and we take a
segment of in memory tree and we take a
segment of on disk tree and these
segments store the same range of keys
meaning that keys from like a specific
for instance letter to a specific letter
let's say from K to Z or something like
that and we take these segments and we
merge them and then we write them down
on disk what that means is that at any
given point in time our database resides
either on the disk or in memory and we
migrate the data slowly from memory to
the disk by these gradual merges right
mmm
and it turned out that this design had
several inefficiencies and the paper
progresses to explain like why
two-component Ellis entries are not like
good enough for whatever the authors
were trying to achieve and they describe
so-called multi-component LSM trees and
so the authors further say that okay
this is not good enough so what we're
going to do is we're going to compact
these tables that we just flushed so
whenever we have more than let's say
four tables that we have flushed from
memory and written to the disk we're
going to take all of them and compact
them meaning that we are going to merge
them into a single bigger table and
every single key that was overwritten or
superseded by like its next version is
just going to be discarded and this way
would we reduce the amount of memory
that we're using for pretty much all the
data and we can reclaim all the space
that we were wasting so to say why would
I use an Alice M tree-like versus a
b-tree so the traditional response or
there is response that nobody was fired
for so far is you know there's like
nobody got fired for ever fired for a
picking Oracle so it's the same in some
way nobody was ever fired for saying
that LSM trees are good for writes and
that's sort of a traditional response to
that and one of the reasons to respond
this way is if you think about a B tree
whenever you have to perform an update
you have to locate the place where
you're gonna perform this right like by
while you're writing write because
you're trying to optimize everything for
the lookup that means that if you you
have to find a place before you can make
an an update and of course LSM trees
because they are like built absolutely
differently they don't have that problem
and whenever we are making a right we
are just doing the write to the log and
we are appending
this rights to the memory table and
eventually we know that things are going
to propagate from the memory table and
disk after that we're going to discard
this right ahead log segment we won't
need it anymore because like the keys
are persisted on disk in a different
place yeah so it's interesting they're
almost inverted like conceptual
processes like in one you have to do the
sort when you go to update you like
sorting through and finding where to
update the other one when you do the
read it's like you need to find where
the data is by looking through multiple
places exactly so this is why I was
saying at some point that it's it's sort
of a dichotomy but I think that LSM
trees have like bad rap in terms of like
they are bad for reads like because
everybody says that OLS entries are not
good for us I mean they can be very good
for reads in fact they can be
potentially better for reads in certain
use cases if you well first implemented
right and second use like all the
optimizations that are available for you
so I would say that jury's out on this
one still or if somebody tells you that
Alice M trees are bad for reads you can
raise your finger and say well actually
and it sounds like it's a newer area so
maybe all the optimizations haven't
haven't possibly been found I would say
that they were rather known for a long
time but everybody just assumed that if
they are so good for writes they just
cannot possibly be also good for a reads
you know well there's this rum
conjecture I heard about yeah but the
thing is that there is also like this
memory overhead that is like the third
component so it is this the third
overhead sort of allows us to do but
you're absolutely right so there it's
hard to run away from rum conjecture and
we definitely still pay the price in all
the centuries in order to facilitate all
the things that we would like them to
have by simply having to do compaction
and maintenance all the time so this is
where the amplification in LSM trees is
coming from yeah metaphorically it makes
me think of like a filing cabinet and
like the B tree is like
put everything in like a folder in the
right spot and LSM is just I just shove
things in there but then when I need to
read I have to like sort through and
yeah that's a very nice parallel yes
so obviously it's faster just put it in
you know so I was wondering about
examples so what like modern databases
are using what uses b-trees what uses
LSM most of in air quotes traditional
databases are using B trees B plus trees
for instance Epis grass the scale is
using B plus trees or like a variant
which is called like blank trees but
this is something that that is more
related to the way they implement like
concurrent splits and merges rather than
anything else but structurally it's
pretty much the same thing
cassandra is using LSM trees and Roxie B
that we have also mentioned today is
also else m3 based and there are
different databases which are using sort
of hybrid approaches so for instance
there was a paper which was called BW
trees which is an immutable B tree which
is like virtually built on top of Ellis
log structured storage BW trees it's
extremely interesting I definitely
advise everybody to take a look at it if
you have a chance and yeah my skill is
using B plus trees as well it's not like
the world has completely moved from B
trees to LS m trees and B trees are like
completely forgotten it's not the case I
keep seeing both names popping up in new
papers and both things sort of remain
relevant one thing you know when we
talked about B trees you know the kind
of an implication was that we want to
minimize you know how often we have to
chase a pointer on disk which I think
goes back to like you know physical hard
drives but we have like solid-state
drives now does that kind of change the
equation at all so we if we think about
when the trees were implemented or
conceived so to say we of course back
then we didn't have
so we had like spinning discs right on a
spinning disc you have an advantage of
being able to finding a physical point
on the disc and actually overwriting it
so it's almost like you have a pencil
and an eraser and then you come to the
point where you scribbled certain things
and you erase them and then you you know
write things and new that means that the
mutability part of B plus trees or B
trees actually made sense back then
because you can actually mutate things
on discs okay it may be slightly slow
but maybe that was not the highest
priority whenever we're writing to SSE
we can write a single page but we cannot
simply overwrite this page in order to
overwrite it we have to erase it first
and then write it right in new page on
its place but we cannot erase a single
page we have to erase an entire block
and that means that if you have some of
the pages in this block still relevant
still used and some of them pretty much
discarded you have to relocate them to
the new space in order to be able to
erase this block this is this process
called garbage collection and during
garbage collection you hold take the
block relocate everything that is
relevant and erase it after that and of
course by the time that hour if you are
doing extensive writing at some point
you're going to run out of pages and run
out of blocks which are empty and you
will have to start you know this
relocation process and if you are
cycling through a bunch of pages meaning
that you keep in order to make a single
byte of change you keep you know telling
controller that is abstract encouraged
collection and everything away from you
you're telling it could you update this
page and it doesn't tell you a you know
what like in order to updated I have to
do like a bunch of things it just tells
you obedient lis of course I am gonna do
that and it does of course it does like
you know
which collection but under the hood in
fact it's doing like lots and lots of
work which can be avoided of course you
know and one of the ways it can be
avoided is exactly by first of all using
the or trying to write pages only
whenever they're fool so we are not
never writing the page which is like
half empty or we are trying our best not
to write a page that wastes half of its
space and second we're trying not to
update the page in the place so it's
it's better for us to make two rights
and then wait for a while and then merge
them eventually to some new location
then in to update like make several
updates to the same page just like in
the short span of time
it makes it sound that the kind of log
structured merge tree or even the
copy-on-write process would work better
with the solid-state drive is that right
yeah so one of the reasons for instance
file systems use log structures storage
as well is exactly to buffer be able to
buffer things and sort of whenever you
have many small writes instead of you
know updating many small segments like
in random locations you just buffer them
all together in a single like larger
chunk of memory and then write it so it
definitely has huge implications so we
started off talking about your interests
in database internals and I think we
covered you know quite a quite a lot of
detail there what do you think the
future holds for for database and
database storage engines funny that you
asked so I just recently was doing a
summary blog post off the papers of 2019
that were about pretty much databases
storage engines indexes and everything
really do that and one of the trends
that I've noticed is everybody is trying
to move away from
databases that are general purpose
meaning that database doesn't try to
solve like all the problems at once
anymore and I keep seeing more
specialized stores and stores that are
solving like single problem but
extremely efficient efficiently
however this that's only one part of
defining the second part is that there
is a trend to have a self-driving
databases so for instance people are
trying to create search engines that are
tracking what queries you are executing
against them and then K they can adapt
dynamically for instance they can change
whether they're doing like index probing
or sequential scans or they can change
certain properties of the pages they can
make pages larger or smaller depending
on the queries that you're writing
depending on the keys that you have or
some of the databases can even take your
data and migrate it behind the scene and
turn your database like from like OLTP
to all laughs basically or something
like that so or like turn changed the
storage format even so it's just that in
an era of cloud computing I would say
it's difficult to be a database vendor
that forces people to know too much
about their database so database has to
know more and more about their users and
I was really impressed by the trend and
how not every single but very many
papers are actually talking about the
same thing and trying to make it simpler
for users and sort of remove some of the
decisions that users are currently
making from them altogether and maybe in
a cloud setting some of the configurable
--zz are not even available for the
people at all so so you cannot really
like if you use like some sort of cloud
storage you cannot take an instance and
restart it because you're using it via
some sort of an API so you don't even
have a notion of instance anymore and
you cannot really change its tuna bowls
you cannot change like number of threads
concurrency and so forth they have to
abstract it all for you and they have to
do it in some intelligent way you don't
have to think about how to develop the
application in a specific way and
specialize yourself in the database
anymore so every everything is gonna be
just done for you yeah that's that would
be exciting definitely very cool well
Alex thank you for coming on the podcast
I recommend everyone check out your book
I have it over here it's very detailed
and it's kind of like a survey of the of
the literature I think on on databases I
would say yeah I guess we hit some high
points of the early chapters but but
that it covers a lot of content so I'm
sure people would love to check it out
for software engineering radio this is
Adam Gordon Bell thank you for listening
developers take your marks it's time to
upgrade your data platform to inner
systems iris it's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible it's time to
use any data from any source it's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces so what are
you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborates
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today inner system's
iris Data Platform the fastest way to
build applications ready set code start
coding for free visit inner systems.com
slash tried to try iris
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening